בוקר טוב Boker Tov so today's דף daf is דף ט"ו, Daf
Tes Vav, we're two lines from the bottom on י"ד עמוד ב',
Yud Daled Amud Bet, we're picking up the next part of the
משנה: Mishnah: ערכין. Erchin. So it says ערכין המטלטלין, Erchin Ha-Metaltelin, the
movable ערכין Erchin and again ערך Erech is when somebody says in
you know the ערך Erech of this person is on me
to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and the תורה Torah gives values
based on the person's age and sex what how much that is.
So what does it mean the ערכין Erchin which are movable? אמר
רב גידל, Amar Rav Gidal, מאי ערכין המטלטלין? mai Erchin Ha-Metaltelin? אמר
רב גידל אמר רב, Amar Rav Gidal amar Rav, באומר ערך כלי
זה עלי. bo-omer Erech kli zeh alai. It means if you make
an ערך Erech of a of cattle of a vessel. Now that's
not true the תורה Torah doesn't recognize the meaning of those words
because ערך Erech only exists by people. So then what would that
mean? דאמר רב גידל אמר רב, De-amar Rav Gidal amar Rav, האומר
ערך כלי זה עלי ha-omer Erech kli zeh alai נותן דמיו. noten
damav. That we translate in that context when you say the ערך
Erech even though it has a technical meaning we translate that to
mean the value of it, not some fixed value set in the
charts in the תורה Torah because that's only for people. מאי טעמא
mai ta'ama why? אדם יודע שאין ערך לכלי Adam yode'a she-ein Erech
le-kli because you know that it doesn't really exist that it's only
for actual vessels. וגמר ואמר לשום דמים vegamar ve-amar leshum damim and
what he really means is its market value. משום הכי נותן דמיו.
mishum hachi noten damav. That's why so in that case where you're
really just taking on yourself the obligation to pay the value of
a vessel, so that would require a בית דין Beis Din of
three. I have to tell you this happens actually, not in this
case, but I've gotten more than one שאלה shayla about somebody said
I took a נדר neder to do X Y and Z and
they want to know if they need התרת נדרים. hataras nedarim. And
you don't take a נדר neder to do something, you take a
שבועה shvuah to do something, a נדר neder is when you say
a certain thing is forbidden to you. And but the question is
okay is that binding or not? So there's a whole discussion about
נדר בלשון שבועה neder belashon shvuah and שבועה בלשון נדר shvuah belashon
neder because people use the term to mean something even though technically
it's the wrong term. Okay so anyway the same thing here if
you said ערך כלי, Erech kli, technically it's the wrong term but
we translate it to mean the value of the כלי. kli.
I understand but we're not learning נדרים Nedarim now. Okay so now
the גמרא Gemara says האי ערכין המטלטלין, hai Erchin Ha-Metaltelin, ערכין של
מטלטלין מיבעי ליה? Erchin shel metaltelin miba'lei? It doesn't mean that the
ערכין Erchin themselves are movable, it means the ערך Erech of cattle.
So that's not the right it doesn't fit the grammar. So fine
תני ערכין של מטלטלין Tanei Erchin shel metaltelin fine have it read
that switch the text or say that's what it means. רב חסדא
אמר Rav Chisda amar that's one explanation. רב חסדא אמר Rav Chisda
amar אבימי Avimi במתפיס מטלטלין לערכין be-matpis metaltelin le-Erchin that you basically
say the ערך Erech of this person on me and then you
set aside some of your cattle, you know whatever your china or
whatever it is and say this'll go towards that value towards the
amount I'm obligated in. And so that's the case and then you
need to redeem that מטלטלין metaltelin you need three. במת—so the גמרא
Gemara says האי ערכין המטלטלין, hai Erchin Ha-Metaltelin, מטלטלין של ערכין מיבעי
ליה. metaltelin shel Erchin miba'lei. It's not that the ערכין Erchin themselves
are cattle it's מטלטלין metaltelin that have been designated to pay for
the ערכין. Erchin. So fine תני מטלטלין של ערכין Tanei metaltelin shel
Erchin read it that way. רבי אבהו אמר Rabbi Abbahu amar that's
answer number two. Now answer number three. באומר ערכי עלי, ba-omer Erki
alai, so you take you accept the value of yourself or somebody
else on you. בקרקע ba-karka and this is the answer the ירושלמי
Yerushalmi gave. לגבות ממנה מטלטלין ligvos mimena metaltelin if you're being asked
now to pay up and for with cattle, בשלושה be-shlosha you get
three to assess how much your cattle is worth right. בקרקעות be-karka'ot
if you want to pay up with land בעשרה be-asara with ten.
Which at least more parallels the idea of redeeming land redeeming cattle
although again here it's how you're what you're paying with not what
you're redeeming. אמר ליה רב אחא מדפתי לרבינא, Amar leh Rav Acha
mi-Difti le-Ravina, בשלמא לאפוקי מהקדש bishlama la-apukei me-hekdesh and this is sort
of similar to the point that Michael made. I get it when
you're coming there's a difference between cattle and land when you've sanctified
the thing. Then what you're doing is you're taking the thing out
of הקדש hekdesh so if you're taking land away from הקדש hekdesh
you might need a bigger בית דין Beis Din you might need
ten. Or or and
when it's cattle you need three right. לאפוקי מהקדש בעינן שלושה. la-apukei
me-hekdesh ba'inan shlosha. אלא לעייולי להקדש ela le-ayulei le-hekdesh so this isn't
just the three-ten distinction this is who needs a בית דין Beis
Din altogether right? You're just assessing the value and writing a check.
So if you want to sort of say that בית דין Beis
Din is part of a a ritual it's a ritual of redeeming
but what you're doing is you're taking something away from הקדש hekdesh
especially you understand who's representing הקדש hekdesh in this transaction it doesn't
mean that there's a גזבר gizbar here you might need the בית
דין Beis Din to represent הקדש's hekdesh interest and you're taking something
away where's the other side? But if you're just giving something to
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash so why would you need a בית
דין? Beis Din? Okay so you said your ערך Erech you want
to figure out whether to give land or cattle or whatever who
needs a
בית דין? Beis Din? אלא לעייולי להקדש שלושה למה לי? ela le-ayulei
le-hekdesh shlosha lama li? אמר ליה סברא הוא amar leh svara hu
nah it's all it makes sense. מה לי לעייולי מה לי לאפוקי
ma li le-ayulei ma li le-apukei what difference does it make if
you're put giving to הקדש hekdesh or you're taking out. אפוקי מאי
טעמא apukei mai ta'ama because at the end of the day why
would you need a בית דין Beis Din when you're redeeming you
know land or cattle? Not just to make it into a ritual
but דיומא di-oma because you might made a mistake in estimating the
value. So לעייולי נמי le-ayulei nami so when you're estimating the value
of land or cattle that you're giving to הקדש hekdesh because to
satisfy your you know your you know your
donation so נמי דיומא nami di-oma maybe you'll make a mistake. making
the value, so you need the בית דין bet din *beis din*
not so much for the exact ritual of redeeming, but to ensure
that you've set the right price. And therefore it actually does make
sense if that's really the reason, so whether you're redeeming land or
whether you're paying the value of land and you didn't actually sanctify
the land itself, or you're paying in land for money that you
owe, in all those cases, if land is a harder thing to
estimate its value, you need a larger בית דין bet din *beis
din* and larger group. Now whether it's really a בית דין bet
din *beis din* then since really what you really need is like
an expert, right? It's like you're buying a house, you get an
inspector to come, right? Those are the types of things you need.
So we'll see about that in a minute, we're going to get
to who makes up this group of people. Okay. רבי יהודה אומר
*Rebbe Yehuda omer*. Now רבי יהודה *Rebbe Yehuda* says that you need
a כהן *Kohen* has to be one of them, one of the
ten. So אמר ליה רב פפא לאביי בשלמא לרבי יהודה היינו דכתיב
כהן אלא לרבנן כהן למה לי *amar leih Rav Pappa le-Abaye bishlama
le-Rebbe Yehuda hayinu dikesiv Kohen ela lerabbanan Kohen lamah li*? But according
to the רבנן *rabbanan* that they say it's just ten and you
don't even have to have a כהן *Kohen* as part of the
ten, why does the תורה Torah *Torah* speak about a כהן *Kohen*?
Because you discussed this yesterday, right? In the פרשה *parsha* where it
talks about sanctifying land or ערכין *Erchin* or בהמה *behemah*, it mentions
כהן *Kohen*, כהן *Kohen*, כהן *Kohen*. You add them all up, you
get to ten. Okay, but fine, so if at least if you
say one of them has to be ten, you understand the discussion
of כהן *Kohen*. But if you say at the end of the
day you don't even need a כהן *Kohen* to do any of
it, why is it written in the פסוקים pesukim *pesukim*? All right,
קשיא *kashya*. We don't know. Now הקרקעות תשעה וכהן *hakar'kaos tish'ah ve-kohen*,
right? Because isn't that what רבי יהודה *Rebbe Yehuda* said? Am I
reading it, remembering it correctly?
He says רבי יהודה אומר אחד מהם כהן *Rebbe Yehuda
omer echad mahem Kohen*.
Oh, no, oh, I'm sorry, right, right, right, right, right, I'm sorry,
right. I'm sorry, right, I thank you, I thought, right. The חכמים
chachamim *hachamim* for the land, nine plus a כהן *Kohen* is what,
meaning ten, one of which is a כהן *Kohen*, is what everybody
says. רבי יהודה *Rebbe Yehuda* says a כהן *Kohen* is one of
them even for the three. Right, right, right. So that's true. So
meaning, so right, we had three פרשיות *parshiyot* in the תורה Torah.
*Torah*, right? What was it? It was one was
ערכין *Erchin*, one was בהמה *behemah*, and one was קרקע karka, *karka*,
right? And I think this had three כהנים *Kohanim*, if I remember
correctly, and this had three כהנים *Kohanim*, and this had four כהנים
*Kohanim*. So by the time you get to קרקע karka, *karka*, if
you add them all up, you get ten. Okay, but but these
redemptions are a בית דין bet din *beis din* of three, okay?
Right, so when you're redeeming מטלטלין metaltelin *metaltelin* or ערכין *Erchin*, these
were the first things mentioned in the משנה *mishnah*, that's a בית
דין bet din *beis din* of three. And רבי יהודה *Rebbe Yehuda*
says, so here when we say ten for קרקע karka, *karka*, everybody
says that really it means nine plus one כהן *Kohen*. So everybody
agrees that כהן *Kohen* at least means something in the קרקע karka.
*karka* case. But here only רבי יהודה *Rebbe Yehuda* says that in
these cases, this בית דין bet din *beis din* of three, one
of them has to be a כהן *Kohen*. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* is saying, well then why according to the חכמים *hachamim* does
it say כהן *Kohen* here for the if in the end of
the idea it's a straight בית דין bet din *beis din* of
three? So that we don't know. But at least when you get
to קרקע *karka*, why else by קרקע *karka* do we add it
up and we don't add it up here, as what the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* asked yesterday? But at least by קרקע *karka*, when we
say ten, there everybody does agree that the use of the word
כהן *Kohen* is to tell you that at least one of them
has to be a כהן *Kohen*. You are representing הקדש hekdesh, *hekdesh*'s
interests after all. Okay, so and again, the question always is, is
this purely like a ממונות *mammon-ist* to estimate or are we sort
of also ritualizing the process of redemption? So מנא הני מילי *minani
hani mili*? How do we know that for קרקע *karka* it's ten
plus a כהן *Kohen*? אמר שמואל עשרה כהנים כתובין בפרשה *amar Shmuel
asarah Kohanim kesuvim baparsha*. It says כהן *Kohen* ten times. חד לגופיה
*chad legufo*, one to say you need a כהן *Kohen*. הנך הוי
מיעוט אחר מיעוט *hanach havei miyut achar miyut*, and the rest is
all saying כהן *Kohen*, כהן *Kohen*, כהן *Kohen*, כהן *Kohen*, כהן *Kohen*.
You gotta love the way the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* does this. If
you're constantly insisting on something and doing, you know, sort of
minimize, like saying you know, limiting and limiting and limiting, every next
time you limit, you're really expanding. ואין מיעוט אחר מיעוט אלא לרבות
*ve-ein miyut achar miyut ela lerabbos*. So you don't really need a
כהן *Kohen*. All the next nine כהנים *Kohanim* are saying even ישראל
*Yisrael*, ואפילו תשעה ישראל ואחד כהן *va'afillu tish'ah Yisrael ve'echad Kohen*. So
מתקיף לה רב הונא בריה דרב נתן אימא Eima, חמישה כהנים וחמישה
ישראלים *maskif lah Rav Huna brei de-Rav Nassan eima chamisha Kohanim ve-chamisha
Yisre'eilim*? So look, why don't you say like this? The first כהן
*Kohen* means כהן *Kohen*. The second כהן *Kohen* is a מיעוט אחר
מיעוט *miyut achar miyut* to mean ישראל *Yisrael*. So now we're back
to ישראל *Yisrael*. So then the next כהן *Kohen* means כהן *Kohen*.
And then the next כהן *Kohen* after you've said כהן *Kohen* now
means ישראל *Yisrael*. So at the end of the day you should
have five כהנים *Kohanim* and five ישראלים *Yisre'eilim*. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says, all right, קשיא *kashya*. I don't know what to say.
Okay, ואדם כיוצא בהם *ve-adam kayotze bahem*. Now we saw in the
ירושלמי Yerushalmi: *Yerushalmi* again that it thought that this meant a slave,
but because the idea that you only redeem a slave in private,
it said it meant a freeman. But then we didn't know why,
how does a freeman become הקדש hekdesh, *hekdesh*? So let's see what
the בבלי Bavli *Bavli* does with this. אדם Adam, מי קדוש kadosh
*Adam mi kadosh*? Since when does a free person become קדוש *kadosh*?
אמר רבי אבהו באומר דמי עלי *amar Rebbe Abahu be'omer demay alai*.
So it doesn't literally mean that you sanctified a free person, you
said I will pay the value of a free person. Now if
you said ערך *Erkh*, it's the value that the in the תורה
Torah *Torah* is sort of charts. But if you said the דמים
*damim*, not the ערך *Erkh*, but the דמים *damim*, the which means
like the market value, then you assess it based on how much
that person would sell as a slave. דתניא האומר דמי עלי שמין
אותו כעבד הנמקר בשוק *detanya ha'omer demay alai shamin oso ke'eved hanimkar
bashuk*. You see how much he would sell as a slave. ועבד
איתקש לקרקעות *ve'eved itkes lehakar'kaos*. And once you're being assessed like a
slave, then you're redeemed with ten. But notice again, you're not קדוש
*kadosh*. You don't sanctify a free person. Okay, you're just saying I
will pay my
value. If you're not sanctifying land but it relates to land, you're
paying with land, or you're paying the value of land, but not
that the land has been sanctified, you still need ten. So here
too you're paying the value of a person assessed as a slave,
you're not really redeeming the person, but you still need ten. Now
תוספות Tosafot asks the question that I'm just going to read because
it parallels what we saw
in
the ירושלמי: Yerushalmi אדם מקדוש. Adam mikadosh. תוספות Tosafot says: ואם תאמר
ולוקמה בעבד דקדוש כדאמרינן בסמוך דמועלין בשערו ובפרק השולח המקדיש נכסיו והיו
בהן עבדים אין הגזבר רשאי להוציאן לחירות. Ve-im tomar ve-lokmah be-eved de-kadosh
ke-damrinan be-samuch de-mo'alin bi-se'aro u-ve-perek ha-sholeach ha-makdish nechasav ve-hayu bahen avadim ein
ha-gizbar rashai le-hotzian le-cherut. So why not just say it's slaves?
ויש לומר דאדם לא משמע ליה דקאי אעבד. Ve-yesh lomar de-adam lo
mashma leh de-kai a-eved. אדם, Adam we have a way of saying
עבד, eved, we would have said עבדים כיוצא בהם. avadim ke-yotzei ba-hem.
אדם normally is not used to refer to slaves, it would mean
a free
person. אינמי הכא פרכי ליבא דרבי דאמר המקדיש עבדו יצא לחירות. Inami
hacha parchi liba de-Rabbi de-amar ha-makdish avdo yatza le-cherut. There's an opinion
if you sanctify your slave, the act of sanctifying him makes him
go free. So then obviously you can't talk about the idea here
being a slave. But anyway תוספות asks why. The ירושלמי Yerushalmi started
assuming it meant a slave, said no no it means a free
person, but then the ירושלמי never explained, so what does that mean
to be redeeming a free person, you know, or to sanctifying a
free person. So the two combined are getting you to the same
place, okay? That you basically, you have committed to paying a person's
value and you use a בית דין bet din of ten to
determine its value and how much you own. And you do it
based on how much the person would sell as a slave. So
now the בבלי has a nice little
digression. בעי רבי אבין, Ba'ei Rabbi Avin, שער העומד לגזוז בכמה. se'ar
ha-omed ligzoz be-kama. So if somebody said I'm going to pay this
person's value to the
הקדש, Hekdesh? what about do you include in the value the hair
that's ready to be the person's ready for a haircut. So do
you include that in their value? Or is the hair like מטלטלין
metaltelin and then though it is קדוש I guess but then for
the you only need a בית דין bet din of three to
redeem the value of to determine the value of the hair. And
you need a בית דין bet din of ten is the hair
considered to be like a slave, like קרקע, or is it considered
to be like מטלטלין for whether you need a בית דין Beis
Din of ten or a בית דין Beis Din of three?
כגזוז דמי ובשלשה או כמחובר דמי ובעשרה. Ke-gazuz dami u-vi-shlosha o ke-mechubar
dami u-ve-asara. Is it like it's already shaved from this person's head
and therefore it needs a בית דין Beis Din of three, or
it's like it's attached and it's like it's part of the person
who's now seen as a slave and therefore it needs ten. So
תא שמע, ta shema, המקדיש את עבדו. ha-makdish et avdo. So now
we're going to talk about actually sanctifying a person, sanctifying a slave,
אין מועלין בו. ein mo'alin bo. There's no מעילה me'ilah because מעילה
me'ilah doesn't apply to קרקע, and slaves are like קרקע, so you
transgress by taking from הקדש, but you don't bring a קרבן מעילה,
korban me'ilah, it doesn't have all the laws of מעילה. me'ilah. רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל אומר מועלין בשערו. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer mo'alin
bi-se'aro. No, no, the hair, laws of מעילה me'ilah apply to because
the hair is not considered to be like it's part of the
slave, it's not considered therefore to be like
land. וקיימא לן, ve-kaima lan, so what's the debate? So we've established
דבשער העומד לגזוז פליגי. de-bi-se'ar ha-omed ligzoz pligi. The question is when
the hair is ready to be cut, so whether that's considered to
be part of the slave or not. So it should be the
same debate here. שמע מינה. shema mina. So the גמרא Gemara says:
that's a good point. You're right, the same way they debate there
whether there's מעילה me'ilah by the
hair, that would translate into whether you would need a בית דין
Beis Din of three or a בית דין Beis Din of ten.
Is it considered part of the slave or not part of the
slave? And now the גמרא Gemara says: okay, so that's whether hair
is part of a person when it's ready to be shaved. It's
interesting, this question comes up in some פוסקים poskim about whether when
a woman's hair is ready to get cut, is it a חציצה
chatzitzah problem to go to the מקוה mikveh because it's
like the hair is already cut and the end of the hair
which would be exposed is exposed and now the fact that it's
still attached is a חציצה chatzitzah to the part that is still,
you know, it's a little crazy, right? As one, there's no חציצה
chatzitzah on a part of the body that has never been exposed.
But it is discussed in the פוסקים poskim also about when fingernails
are ready to be cut. Is the fact that it's ready to
be cut make it seem like well this part is now extraneous,
so that's like a חציצה chatzitzah on the part of the fingernail
that will be exposed once I cut it? The general assumption is
that that's crazy, there's no you can't have a חציצה chatzitzah on
a part of the body that's, you know, has yet to be
exposed. But anyway, but here at least it's the relevant question of
is it considered to be attached or detached for this purpose of
מעילה me'ilah and a בית דין Beit Din of three or a
בית דין Beit Din of ten. So now the גמרא Gemara wants
to tie it into a parallel debate. נימא הני תנאי כהני תנאי,
nema hani tannai ke-hani tannai, let's say these תנאים tannaim are the
same as the following
תנאים. tannaim. דתנן, de-tnan, רבי מאיר אומר יש דברים שהן כקרקע ואינם
כקרקע. Rabbi Meir omer yesh devarim she-hen ke-karka ve-einam ke-karka. There are
things that are like land and not exactly like land, ואין חכמים
מודים לו, ve-ein chachamim modim lo, and the חכמים don't agree. כיצד
עשר גפנים טעונות מסרתי לך, keitzad esar gefanim te'unot masarti lach, I
gave you to watch for me ten vines that were laden with
grapes, והלה אומר אינם אלא חמש. ve-haleh omer einam ela chamesh. There
are only five. So is that a מודה במקצת modeh be-miktzat and
you take an oath? The point is you don't take an oath
on קרקע. So is the question of the vines laden with grapes,
is that like land or is that like chattel because they're ready
to be harvested? רבי מאיר אומר מחייב, Rabbi Meir omer mechayev, you
do make an oath, וחכמים אומרים כל המחובר לקרקע הרי הוא כקרקע.
ve-chachamim omrim kol ha-mechubar la-karka harei hu ke-karka. If it's attached to
the land, it's like land and there's no
oath. ואמר רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא. ve-amar Rabbi Yossi bi-Rabbi Chanina. בענבים
העומדות ליבצר עסקינן. beanavim haomdot libatzer askinan. The question is that the
grapes are ready to be harvested. מר סבר mar savar כבצורות דמיין,
kivtzurot damyan, it’s like they’re already harvested, so it’s like they’re chattel
and there’s an oath, that’s רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. ומר סבר לאו
כבצורות דמיין. u'mar savar lav kivtzurot damyan. No, they’re still attached to
the ground. So presumably that would be exactly parallel to this question
of how do you look at hair that’s ready to be shaved,
is it like it’s attached or not attached for this question of
הקדש? So the גמרא Gemara says לא, lo, no, it’s not necessarily
the same debate. אפילו תימא רבי מאיר, Afilu tema Rabbi Meir, even
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir there that says the grapes are like they’re
harvested would not necessarily say the same about the
hair. Why? עד כאן לא קאמר רבי מאיר התם Ad kan lo
ka'amar Rabbi Meir hatam אלא כל כמה דשבק להו מיכחשי. ela kol
kama d'shabak lehu mikachshi. There, as long as you leave the grapes
on the vine, they’ll get worse. When the time to harvest comes,
they really have to be harvested now. It’s going to be bad
for them to leave them on. So there where there’s like almost
an imperative to harvest them, he says it’s like they’re already off
the vine and they’re like
chattel. אבל הכא, Aval hacha, but
by the hair, כל כמה דשבק להו אשבוחי משבחי, kol kama d'shabak
lehu ashbuchei mashbechei, the longer you leave it on the
head, the hair grows longer and it’s better to leave it on
the head. So it might be time, but it’s not necessary to
cut it now. And therefore the hair, everybody might agree in that
case it’s considered part of the slave and therefore there’s no מעילה
Meilah and you would have a בית דין Beit Din of ten
not a בית דין beis din of three. Let’s just go a
little bit longer if people have to leave now I understand but
we’re going to go a little bit longer. דיני נפשות. Dinei nefashot.
So now we go to the דיני נפשות Dinei nefashot are 23.
And included in the דיני נפשות Dinei nefashot is the case of
רובע ונרבע, rova v'nirva, a case of bestiality. So the גמרא Gemara
here makes a point. קפסיק ותני, Kapassik vetani, לא שנא רובע זכר,
lo shena rova zachar, it doesn’t matter if the ox, the male
animal
here, had intercourse with a male, ולא שנא רובע נקבה, velo shena
rova nekeva, or if the male animal had intercourse with a
female. בשלמא לרובע נקבה דכתיב, Bishlama lerova nekeva d'chtiv, I get the
case of with a female, it says
והרגת את האשה ואת הבהמה. veharagta et ha'ishah v'et habehemah. אלא רובע
זכר מנלן? Ela rova zachar minalan? So how do you know because
in the תורה where it speaks about killing the ox and the
man who committed an act of bestiality, it only speaks about the
case when the man was the penetrator, not the penetratee, okay? So
where do you know in this case where the ox is the
רובע rova that you would actually kill them both and that the
ox would get a בית דין beis din of 23? That’s not
an explicit case in the תורה. So it says דכתיב כל שוכב
עם בהמה מות יומת. d'chtiv kol shochev im behemah mot yumat. Because
here it says one who lies with an animal, which means the
man is the penetrator, so gets put to death. And it says
אם אינו ענין לשוכב, im eino inyan l'shochev, now we don’t need
it to tell me that because another פסוק pasuk in ויקרא Vayikra
says איש אשר יתן שכבתו. ish asher yiten shichavto. So there are
two פסוקים Psukim. by the man describing the same scenario where the
man is the שוכב. shochev. So you don’t need them both to
tell you that case. תנהו ענין לנשכב. Tanehu inyan l'nishkav. So one
of them is coming to tell you even if the animal was
the שוכב, shochev, was the penetrator, and the man was the נשכב.
nishkav. So to tell you even that
scenario. ואפקיה רחמנא בלשון שוכב, V'afkeih Rachmana bilshon shochev, so why does
it then frame it like the man is the שוכב? shochev? לאקושי
נשכב לשוכב, l'akushei nishkav l'shochev, to connect the
two. מה שוכב הוא בבית דין של עשרים ושלשה, Mah shochev hu
b'Beis Din shel esrim ushloshah, the same way it says
ואיש אשר יתן שכבתו בבהמה v'ish asher yiten shichavto b'vehemah right that
you should kill both of them, it says
והרגת את האשה ואת הבהמה תהרוגו, veharagta et ha'ishah v'et habehemah taharogu,
so it links the two and they both get so the same
way the man gets a בית דין beis din? of 23 the
animal does. So therefore אף נשכב הוא בבית דין של עשרים ושלשה.
af nishkav hu b'Beis Din shel esrim ushloshah. So basically the point
is that because the פסוק pasuk repeated the scenario, we interpret the
פסוק pasuk to be describing when the roles are reversed. And the
same way when the roles are one way they both get put
to death with a בית דין beis din, of 23, when the
roles are reversed it’s the same thing. Okay, let’s move on to
the
שור הנסקל. shor haniskal. שור הנסקל בעשרים ושלשה. Shor haniskal b'esrim ushloshah.
שנאמר השור יסקל וגם בעליו יומת, shene'emar hashor yissakel vegam ba'alav yumat,
כמיתת הבעלים כך מיתת השור. k'mitat haba'alim kach mitat hashor. The same
way you would kill a person with 23 you kill the ox.
אמר ליה אביי לרבא, Amar lei Abaye l'Rava, so אביי Abaye said
to
רבא, Rava, ממה דהאי וגם בעליו יומת כמיתת הבעלים כך מיתת השור
הוא דאתא? mimah dehai vegam ba'alav yumat k'mitat haba'alim kach mitat hashor
hu de'ata? How do you know it’s telling
you that you
need 23 for the ox? אימא, now here what’s great about this
גמרא Gemara is it actually explores what פשט pshat of
the פסוק pasuk is, maybe you actually put the owner to death.
So אם כן, im ken, no, לכתוב וגם בעליו. lichtov vegam ba'alav.
Why doesn’t it say השור יסקל וגם בעליו? hashor yissakel vegam ba'alav?
Why does it have to say the extra verb יומת? yumat? No,
because יומת בידי שמים, yumat bidei shamayim, okay fine. So therefore יומת
yumat is coming to tell you this הלכה halacha of the שור
shor needs 23 but not that the owner is deserving of death.
So no, גמרא Gemara says אי כתב רחמנא הכי, ei katav Rachmana
hachi, had it said
that, הוה אמינה בסקילה, hava aminah b'skilah, I would have thought you
do סקילה skilah to the person. So בסקילה סלקא דעתך? b'skilah salka
daitach? And that wouldn’t have been possible. So the גמרא no, no,
even if it had not had the word יומת, yumat, I would
never have read it to mean you give סקילה skilah to the
person. Why not? קטיל איהו בסייף, Katil ihu b'sayif, if he directly
killed himself, his death penalty is by the
sword. If he himself was the killer with his own hands, the
death penalty is the sword. So ממונא בסקילה? Mammona besekilah? There would
be no way if his ox did it, he'd get the more
severe death penalty of סקילה. Sekilah. So even if it had just
said
השור יסקל וגם בעליו, Hashor yisakel vegam ba'alav, I would not have
said he would have gotten סקילה. Sekilah. There's no way I would
have given him a heavier death penalty for when his ox did
it than when he did it himself.
If he didn't even have to have
the גזירת הכתוב, Gezeirat Hakatuv, you would have said no. I wouldn't
have said... I wouldn't have read it that way. And therefore you
didn't need the word יומת, Yumat, and the word יומת Yumat is
coming to tell me this extra that it doesn't mean not to
read the whole פסוק Pasuk literally. So the גמרא says
ודילמא האי דכתב רחמנא יומת לאקולי אלויה לאפוקי מסייף לחנק? Udilma hai
dechtav Rachmana Yumat l’akulei aloyei l’apukei misayif l’chenek? Okay, so fine, but
still don't say יומת Yumat means don't treat the whole thing literally
just to tell me a בית דין beis din of 23. Say
יומת Yumat means if you did it yourself, you would have gotten
executed by the sword. Now that it was your ox that did
it, יומת, Yumat, you're put to death with a lighter death penalty
with חנק. Chenek. Maybe that's the פשט Pshat of the
פסוק? Pasuk? No. הניחא למאן דאמר חנק חמור. Haniha leman de'amar chenek
chamur. That I can get it if you say that חנק Chenek
is a more weighty death penalty than the sword. Then there's no
way to read the פסוק Pasuk to say it's coming to go
easy on you. אלא למאן דאמר חנק קל, Ela leman de'amar chenek
kal, but our assumption is that חנק Chenek is a lighter death
penalty, מאי איכא למימר? Mai ika lemimar? So the גמרא is saying
is no, that's exactly the point. Why do you read it to
do this דרשה Drasha that you need a בית דין of 23
for the ox? Why not read it like the owner gets death
and say
השור יסקל וגם בעליו יומת Hashor yisakel vegam ba'alav yumat and וגם
בעליו יומת Vegam ba'alav yumat means you're going to get a lighter
death penalty than had you done it yourself? Had you done it
yourself, you would have gotten the sword. Now that it was your
ox, you get a lighter death penalty of חנק. Chenek. And that's
a nice פשט Pshat reading of the פסוק. Pasuk. What tells us
not to read the פסוק Pasuk that way?
That's the question. מאי איכא למימר? Mai ika lemimar? How... so that's
a good read of the פסוק, Pasuk, so why don't we read
it that way?
לא סלקא דעתך דכתיב אם כפר יושת עליו Lo salka da'atach dechtiv
im kofer yushas alav because it says here that you can redeem
yourself. ואי סלקא דעתך בר קטלא הוא, Ve'i salka da'atach bar katla
hu, if you were deserving of death, והכתיב לא תקחו כופר לנפש
רוצח Vehaktiv lo tikchu kofer lenefesh rotzeach that we wouldn't allow an
atonement payment if a person was a murderer. So the גמרא says
אדרבה משום היא גופא. Adaraba mishum hi gufa. That's exactly why the
תורה allows a כופר Kofer payment here. קטל איהו, Katal ihu, if
you, the guy yourself, the man himself is the murderer, לא תשקליה
בממונא, Lo tishkaliya bemammona, he cannot pay it off with money, אלא
בקטלא, Ela bikatla, he has to be put to death. לא תקחו
כופר לנפש רוצח. Lo tikchu kofer lenefesh rotzeach. If you're a רוצח.
Rotzeach. But קטל שורו, Katal shoro, but if your ox kills, then
לפרוק נפשיה בממונא, Liprok nafshaya bemammona, then you should be able to
redeem yourself. Thank you, that is total פשט Pshat of the פסוקים.
Psukim Right? The פשט Pshat of the פסוקים Psukim. is וגם בעליו
יומת, Vegam ba'alav yumat, the owner should be put to death, but
because it's only the ox that killed and not he
himself, אם כפר יושת עליו. Im kofer yushas alav. Normally we don't
allow a כופר Kofer for a murderer, but for this case, we
allow a כופר. Kofer. That's total פשט Pshat of the פסוקים. psukim
Okay, that יומת Yumat is literal, but it's a יומת Yumat that
allows for the payment of a כופר. Kofer. Okay, why do we
not read it that way? So the גמרא says
אלא אמר חזקיה ותני דבי חזקיה אמר קרא יומת המכה רוצח הוא.
Ela amar Chizkiyah vetanei d’vei Chizkiyah amar kra yumat hamakeh rotzeach hu.
So על רציחתו אתה הורגו, Al retzichato atah horgo, if he's רוצח
הוא, Rotzeach hu, if he's the murderer you kill him. ואי אתה
הורגו על רציחת שורו. Ve'i atah horgo al retzichat shoro. So you're
right, פשט Pshat of the פסוק Pasuk is this guy is deserving
the death penalty, he can buy himself off with a כופר, Kofer,
which obviously is very, you know, is very... means that the wealthy
people get out of it and the poor people don't get out
of it, right? Which is a bit... but anyway, but poor people
would then be put to death, right?
Let's just appreciate why... what some of the implications of why חז"ל
Chazal would not want to read it, you know, besides textual reasons,
why would they not want to read it this way? A, it
would mean that poor people would get put to death and rich
people would get off, right? And B, it would basically mean that,
you know, that... that you would be put to death for negligence
and not for actual committing of murder, which is what it's saying
here. רוצח, Rotzeach, you know, על רציחתו אתה הורגו. Al retzichato atah
horgo. We get that you're responsible for death, but that's not a
reason to execute somebody if they're... if it's negligence rather than if
they actually were a murderer. So those are the things that are
pushing them to read it that you're never... you never put the
guy to death. It's always a payment of money. Now some ראשונים
Rishonim still say that what it's still telling you is a moral
point. It's not... it's not saying you are put to death unless
you pay the כופר, Kofer, it's saying you're deserving of being put
to death but we're never going to do that. Instead, we're going
to impose a כופר Kofer payment. It's sort of like the way
some explain עין תחת עין, Ayin tachat ayin, which means why is
that ממונא? Mammona? It means you're deserving of this punishment, but we're
never going to actually implement it, instead you're going to pay money.
Okay, so that's sort of how we get to that reading here.
And we'll just finish now to the two dots, with that we'll
end for today. Okay. איבעיא
להו שור סיני בכמה? Iba'ya lehu shor Sinai bekama? When when it
says, you know, when it says אם בהמה אם איש לא יחיה
Im behema im ish lo yichyeh when they drew close to הר
סיני, Har Sinai, would you need to have a בית דין of
23? Twenty-three to put the ox to death. Now פשט pshat of
the פסוקים psukim is that they would kill the animal or the
person immediately at the moment, because what when the פסוק pasuk says
כי סקול יסקל או ירה יירה. ki sakol yisakeil o yaro yiyareh.
So what that means is, how do you kill them if they're
drawing close? You're not allowed to draw close to the mountain. What
do you do if an animal or person is drawing close? You
kill them by throwing stones at a distance or shooting arrows at
a distance. That's ירה יירה. yaro yiyareh. But the Rabbis read it
that no, if they did that afterwards you go ahead and you
give the guy stands in front of a בית דין and either
gets סקילה skila or gets thrown off a cliff. That's the way
they read כי סקול יסקל או ירה יירה. ki sakol yisakeil o
yaro yiyareh. So they understand that that actually is a basis for
the punishment of סקילה skila and the people would be judged with
a בית דין if they drew close to הר סיני. Har Sinai.
So what if the ox drew close to הר סיני? Har Sinai?
Would the ox be judged with a בית דין? That's the question.
Then who would have executed the sentence?
No, it says כי סקול יסקל או ירה יירה. ki sakol yisakeil
o yaro yiyareh. You stone it or them. Okay, so מי גמר
שעה מדורות או לא? mi gmar sha'ah midoros o lo? Do you
learn out from that sort of that thing that was only for
that moment from the law for all future generations?
תא שמע דתני רמי בר יחזקאל, tashma detani Rami bar Yechezkel, אם
בהמה אם איש לא יחיה. im beheimah im ish lo yichye. מה
איש בכ"ג, ma ish bekhaf-gimmel, the same way of course we would
never execute a person without a בית דין, אף בהמה בכ"ג, af
beheimah bekhaf-gimmel, even the animal. So now we've got in that clearly
the פשט pshat of those פסוקים is that they're killed at the
moment, translating those into cases of a בית דין and even applying
to the ox. Okay, we will continue with this tomorrow.